Last night there.
There we go.
That's right and live on Facebook.
Okay, we're still getting some participants in here. Welcome, everyone. To the radar live webinar. We'll get things started in a minute here, just turning on the live settings on Facebook here, so that our friends from the community can join in.
As well.
Hmm.
Okay, that doesn't seem to be available as an option.
Interesting.
Okay, we are going to skip that one. Right.
Welcome, uh… Right, let's get this thing on the road. Good evening, everyone, and welcome to the Reducing insurance dependence academy or RIDA live event. We are here to help you build a practice with healthier margins, a happier team, and most importantly.
Patients who choose you for the quality of your care, and not just the name on your insurance card. I'm your host, Dan Adisha, and tonight's session, Stop Working Harder for Less, The Anti-PPO Growth System is designed to give you the exact roadmap.
To make that a reality. And because growth requires influence, we are proud to be sponsored tonight by Echo Marketing. Echo specializes in helping healthcare professionals dominate their local markets, ensuring that as you step away from insurance dependence.
You're stepping in to a flood of high value patients who value your expertise.
Now, we have packed itinerary with 5 incredible panelists tonight. So if you're ready to reclaim your practice, your peace of mind, well, you are in the right place.
Um, just a quick few housekeeping notes to get you the most of this event. First, yeah, we are recording, uh, so you will receive a replay link after the event. You can rewatch and share it with your partners. However, do not let that make you passive, because.
The real value is happening right here, right now, live.
To make the best use of your time, engage with us. Use the Q&A button at the bottom of your screen for specific questions you would like for me to ask the panelists, and use the chat to share your thoughts with your colleagues here. I have my eyes on both the feeds. I will do my best to weave your questions into the conversation as we go, or we will tackle them during the Q&A session.
Closer to the end of the event.
Now, uh… Let's take a look at the program we have lined up for you tonight. We're going to start the engine immediately with our insurance and business panel from 705 to 7.
40, uh, with Ken Kaufman and Dominica Obrisadic. He pulled back the curtain on the financial realities of PPOs. They'll be sharing the safe sequencing playbook, how to strategically reduce your dependence without hurting your bottom line.
Then, at 740, we are going to shift gears into the local SEO and practice ownership, a marketing Q&A segment with Naren Aralraja. This is a critical piece of the… RIDA philosophy. If you aren't on the list, insurance list, you must be the obvious choice in your zip code. Naren will show you how to dominate your local market so that high-value patients find you first.
Then add, uh… Yeah, then we'll move on into our operations and patient experience panel with Dr. Michael Sonic and Daniel Kramer to discuss the systems, the messaging, and the clinical excellence that is required to turn.
Any lead into a loyal patient. This is where we talk about the human connection that transcends any insurance card. And finally, we will close out the night with a live Q&A. I'll be monitoring the chat throughout the night, so please.
Drop your questions as they come to you. Our experts are here to give you candid, real-world answers.
Right.
So with that being said, let's dive in right into the insurance and business panel here.
Uh… Our first guest believes that numbers aren't just math. They are a story of.
Freedom from well or frustration. As the co-host of the Dental Truth Project, he has spent his career helping practice owners stop guessing and start leading through data. He specializes in turning complex financial fog into clear, actionable insights. Please welcome the man who helps doctors reclaim their profit margins.
Ken Kaufman. Ken, wonderful to have you here at the panel.
Thank you. So glad to be here. Thanks for this opportunity.
Absolutely.
Okay.
Right. Um… So next up, we have Danielle Kramer. Danielle is a respected dental industry leader and a business strategist with over 20 years of experience helping practices grow and thrive. Now.
yeah, with the background spanning both clinical and administrative roles. She understands the human side of the dental business. She helps teams build the systems and the confidence needed to deliver exceptional care without the PPO safety net.
So joining us to elevate your patient experience is Daniel Kramer.
Thank you for having me. Happy to be here with you guys.
Fantastic. So let's get into the main Q&A segment here. Okay.
Hmm. Seems like I have made a mistake. I have made a mistake. So… I think. Yeah.
My apologies, it seems that, uh, instead of Daniel, it'll be Dominica.
will be on the panel here with us. Give me a second.
Okay.
Right.
Yep. So my apologies there, ladies and gentlemen. It's going to be, uh… It seems that I have, uh… invited the wrong panelists at the wrong time. I do apologize for that. So let me read.
do that real quickly. Danielle, my apologies. It seems that you're in the second panel and not the first one here. So, to all those who were really keen on hearing Danielle speak right here and now, well, you gotta wait just a little bit longer for us to get to her.
So with that being said, the panelists who will be speaking is one who, you know, had the efficiency.
Being the silent. Our next panelist is one who knows that efficiency is the silent engine of a thriving practice.
Um, and she is a master mechanic of that. With over two decades hands-on experience, she doesn't just consult, she transforms how dental teams breathe and function. From compliance to cash flow, she ensures when a practice grows, it does so safely and profitably.
Joining us to streamline your success is Dominica Oprezedik. Dominica, welcome to the panel.
Don. Thank you so much for the kind introduction. I'm happy to be here.
Great. Right. So with that being said, ladies and gentlemen, let's really, this time around, dive into the main Q&A here.
Right on. So, Ken, my first question goes out to you.
When owners start dropping insurance networks but don't touch their overhead, where does the cash flow map usually break down first?
Mm-hmm.
Well, it actually usually breaks down. From a cash perspective, it usually breaks down when the, uh… When the patient… or I'm sorry, when the dental team is trying to figure out what's happening as, like, because all these shifts are happening in the business, right? There's a lot of different things going on, and what happens is they tend to confuse production for actual improvement with cash flow.
Um, and so there's a little bit of a mask that can ultimately show up right at the beginning, and what causes this to happen is.
Um, especially when you're starting to try to drop the PPO dependency, adjusted production will go up initially. Um, and it does it because you're charging higher fees. That makes sense, right? Um, but the challenge here is, is that case acceptance often drops off initially.
AR days start to increase, which sucks cash flow, and then collection timing starts to stretch out further and further, and so your cash flow gets leaner and leaner.
Um, as you go through the process. And so, basically, cash gets worse before it gets better. You always have to remember that when you're going through this process. And the real miss is if you're not doing some type of forecasting with a 13-week cash forecast tool.
Or something like that. If you're not using that, it really will save you to make sure that you're not running out of cash and getting yourself into trouble.
Okay, so cash gets worse before it gets better. How do we know it's a tolerable amount of worse? What is the signal for that? Whereas, you know, how are we to understand that we are really going into the deep end?
And it's not a sign.
Sure. So the way that I like to to think about this, and this is the framework that I like to use here is, if you have less than 3 months of cash runway.
Okay.
You need to slow down. You're going too fast. And if you have strong demand, and your systems are starting to show up, and they're functioning and working well, that's generally where you can start to put the hammer down and start to try to grow.
check. Thanks, Ken, for starting us off on the right foot here and letting us know that it's okay sometimes to see that cash slip away, but… As long as it's forecasted and within.
constraint. Now, Dominica, when an insurance contract renews and the fees come down again.
How do you decide whether the patient volume it brings is still worth accepting?
Can you repeat the question?
Uh, right. So when an insurance contract renews, and the fees come down again, how do you decide whether the patient volume it brings is still worth accepting?
You know, well. That's a really good question. That decision hinges on understanding true profitability, not just patient volume. And there are key factors that we look at when evaluating that scenario.
You want to look at reimbursement versus cost to deliver care. You want to make sure that you're understanding the percentage of active patients on that plan. So if the plan represents anywhere from 15 to 20% of your patient base.
The risk of dropping is much lower. If you want to understand your local competition. If your area is saturated with providers that are in network.
Staying may not give you the security that you think.
Another key factor that you want to understand is your practice's brand strength. Strong online presence, strong patient experience, less patient dependence on PPO is the ultimate goal.
And then another thing, another key factor is negotiating leverage. So some PPOs will renegotiate if you can show utilization, growth, or competitive data. And there are others that don't negotiate at all.
Most dental practices treat. PPO contracts as a fixed infrastructure. The way that you say, like, you treat your rent or your utilities. They renew automatically, often with no fee increase, while your overhead climbs 3 to 6% annually.
So over a 5-year period, a practice can lose anywhere from 15 to 25% of effective revenue that can per.
produced in real dollar purchasing power without a single contract ever being caught or even evaluated.
Feet erosion is. Honestly, rarely dramatic. It's a slow bleed.
The practice looks busy, the schedule is full, but the net collections per procedure declines steadily year over year.
So the question I always ask first, whenever I enter into a dental office is, what is this contract actually costing you per chair hour? Not the write-off in isolation, but what… your effective hourly production looks like on this plan versus your practice average. So say if you're running a hygiene chair at $180, an hour on a PPO. When you're overhead is clearly.
Closer to $210. You're not just breaking even. You're subsidizing that patient's care with profit margin from other procedures.
Right.
While security is real, and I don't dismiss that, but security build on a declining fee structure is false security.
Check. Thanks, Dominica, for that comprehensive answer. Ken. Let's see over here. When deciding how fast to pull back from insurance networks, how do you balance keeping revenue steady against actually improving what the practice keeps?
Yeah, that's a that's a great question, because we ultimately want to keep and we want to keep as much as possible through the process. Burning through cash.
Um, as you're trying to make this transition is gonna be a very, very costly mistake, and so you want to definitely keep your eye on the ball there. Um… The key challenge here is revenue is gonna get choppy, and when revenue gets choppy, people get nervous, people get worried, um, and so the key component here is you have to be ready to understand where those, um…
just where the limitations are as you're trying to time all of these moving pieces and parts. And when I say that specifically, when we get to this, sometimes we want to think about it like a clinical decision.
But the reality is, it is not a clinical decision. This is a balance sheet risk mitigation that has to happen. And so we have to be constantly looking at the balance sheet, looking at our working capital, and making sure that we have plenty of cash, like I said.
If you're… if you're below 3 months, you gotta slow your… your game, and you gotta slow your process down, but if you're starting to get above that, and your systems are in place, you're going to be able to start to get the traction that you're hoping for by moving away from insurance dependence.
What's the ideal system that you're talking about here?
Yeah. So the the ideal system is all of the pieces of the puzzle, and some on this, uh, some others on here know some of these things, even, like, much, much better than I do, but… The key thing is, is when your systems are functioning and working cleanly, um, because you've got the handle on what's happening with everything that's going on with your move from insurance dependence to away to it, the system and process that your team puts together.
ultimately is gonna… that's what's gonna drive the success. And if those team members are not talking together, if they're not coordinating with each other, if hygiene isn't talking to treatment coordination and all of those pieces of the puzzle, it falls apart really quickly.
Even if you were doing everything right. Outside of that.
Check. Got it. And we are going to get a little bit more deeper into the clinical side of things in the next panel, but appreciate the overlook there, Ken.
Uh, Dominica, when a coordinator doesn't have a clear script for walking a patient through what they'll owe out of pocket, especially a patient that's used to insurance covering most of the bill.
What breaks down in that conversation?
When a treatment coordinator doesn't have a structured script, three things happen in rapid succession. They lead with a number, they apologize for the number.
Okay.
And they offer a discount or payment plan before the patient can even answer.
So this is the preemptive surrender pattern that is truly an epidemic in every dental office that has been PPO dependent.
The coordinator has been trained and either explicitly or by culture to buffer the patient shock. And they do so.
Right.
instantaneously without a script, they improvise. They. you can feel the hesitation and improvisation under pressure defaults to a path of least resistance, right? So you reduce the friction by reducing revenue. A lot of times treatment coordinators that are inexperienced or not coached.
They'll start to delay the treatment. They'll postpone the treatment because they're hesitant. They dread that conversation. A standardized script truly changes the sequence. It leads with value, it contextualizes the number.
It presents options without an apology and holds the line on feet integrity while still being compassionate.
The breakdown I see most often isn't loud. It's a quiet one. When I come into dental offices, I like to come in, and I like to, you know, shadow them just to see them in their organic form. And a lot of times what I see is before the patient.
has even responded. The one phrase that tells the patient that the fee is in question is that.
You know, I know, you know, I know that it's it costs a lot, or, um, like, that hesitation about the fee. So a good script removes that ambiguity. It gives the coordinator confidence.
Because they know exactly what to say next, regardless of how the patient will respond.
Confidence is contagious, and patients feel it. I can't stress that enough. And, you know, there are data points that surpass most offices when we implement structured financial scripts. Treatment acceptance.
typically rise, you know, they don't go down. Um, even when out-of-pocket costs are higher. And this is because patients trust a confident presenter over value. Um, I can share with you one recent success story. I have been in a practice for.
Yes.
14 months now, and our last session we just had this past Wednesday, and the end of the conversation we said that we really wished we would have recorded our 1st session for 14 months ago to the one that we had last time.
And how much exponentially that team has grown. They are hitting their goals. They are closing on treatment. They are truly understanding, comprehending that.
Dental care is an investment in your health. It's not a cost that is just reserved for the wealthy or the people that have expendable income.
Check. And that's a really great outlook of dental care itself.
Now, uh, Ken, when hygiene is fully booked, but the restorative schedule is half empty. What's the handoff between scheduling and the treatment team that actually closes that particular gap?
Yeah, just one second before I answer that, I want to follow up with Dominica, because what she said there, it was so critical, and there was something I just want to make sure we put an emphasis on this, and it is when when you're going to go through this change, it is a culture change.
Hmm.
Every single employee is going to be massively impacted by what… what's going to change in their daily routine and the way that they approach their work. And so, Dominique explaining that the client that you were working with there, I mean, that was… it was a perfect way to think about.
The work that needs to go into the people.
Because everything… if the people aren't on board, this whole idea, this whole concept just completely falls apart. So anyways, I wanted to just validate, Dominique, where you were coming from on that, and that's an amazing example that you shared.
Thank you, Ken.
All right. Now, I can't even remember the question you asked me, Don. So you're going to have to lob that over again.
Let's talk about. Sure, so when hygiene is fully booked, but the restorative schedule is half empty, what's the handoff between scheduling and the treatment team that actually can close that gap?
So… Here's how I think about this.
Hmm.
This is a conversation failure between diagnosis and scheduling production. It's just a… it's just a flat-out failure in communication and in building out all the right handoffs.
Uh, and the gap happens when hygiene diagnosis, or sorry, hygiene diagnosis, uh, treatment, uh, but scheduling is still optimizing for fill rate and not case value. And so that's generally where the breakdown starts to happen.
You'll see no prioritization of high-value cases, same-day treatment conversion system.
Mm-hmm.
will be struggling. No accountability between hygiene and treatment coordination and scheduling, which I'd mentioned that before. The fix to all of this, from my perspective, is you need a dollar per hour scheduling target. And with that target, then you can start to make sure that you're going the right way in terms of becoming insurance independent.
Okay, now you spoke a little bit about case value. How are we going to balance that out with overselling?
Is that a question for me?
Yes, Ken, it's just a follow-up. I wanted to understand, because if we're optimizing for case value.
Is that, like, would that, uh, encourage overselling and treatments that are not necessarily needed?
I don't know that I'm even qualified to answer this question, because that's so clinical in nature, and it's it's ultimately up to that provider to make those make those treatment decisions. Obviously, they… you… Each provider is possibly going to look at a patient a little bit different, but the key component here is you've got to get all of the providers on board with all of the discussion that has to happen with them about why fees are higher than they're used to.
check. Thanks, Ken for that answer. And now we are going to actually move into a bit of a organic session over here, answering some of the questions that our registrants have asked us.
No. So my 1st question, let's start.
Again, uh… Dr. Matt Carpenter, a practice owner. Dr. Matt.
is in a situation that many of you might recognize. He is in-network only with Delta.
But that single provider represents 65% of his entire practice. So Ken, for an owner with that many eggs in one basket, how do you even begin the process of dropping that plan without the business collapsing?
Yeah, you can't… you can't drop it. I mean, let's be honest, it's gonna be a minute, it's gonna be a while before you're gonna be able to drop it. But you can start to institute you can start to institute various elements of this, getting your team culture to start to talk about higher case values and different things like that.
And so, um, it's just… you have to… to Dr. Carpenter, like, you've got to saddle up here and know that it's going to take a minute, it's gonna take a while before you can make this full transition. And so the sooner you can start teaching your team to do, like, real treatment coordination and to really, like, get…
get, um, you know, face-to-face with all of those patients and help them understand the value that you're bringing to them, like all of those things are going to be, like, just great to build the foundation so that ultimately you can go there. But it's hard. This is hard work. This is a heavy lift.
There's a reason why most people do not move away from insurance. But once you get to the other side, to the promised land, totally worth it. Totally worth it.
Check. No, Dr. Carpenter, if you're here, you may ask a follow-up question, and I may get to it as well. So feel free. And then, Dominica, we have a question about the fear factor from.
Paul Miranda, a CEO, and Tobin Doyle, a business manager.
They're both asking about leakage. So, Dominica, what is the actual realistic percentage of patients a doctor should expect to lose?
And how many usually choose to stay even when the practice goes out of network?
Hmm.
So you know what? That's a that's a really good question. And you know, and it depends on the patient-based dependency, right? Because if you have a patient-based dependency like the Doctor Carpenter.
then that leakage might be a lot higher than somebody that does not. So.
The appropriate answer would be that you'd have to do a complete audit to understand where your practice stands and come up with a strategy based on.
you're in unique stand, you know, your unique practice. So, you know, a lot of people like that, um, you know, cookie-cutter approach and practice ownership nowadays is really not a cookie-cutter approach. You really have to do the forensics, you have to do the.
dirty work, um, in order for you to be able to make evidence-based decisions.
Right. And uh… Can you take the example of Dr. Carpenter and say if they are, you know, 65% of their entire practice is in this one PPO this time around it's Delta.
Do we have a number for that?
I don't know. Ken, do you have any insight on that?
Yeah, I… I don't… I don't have, like, a very uh like a spot-on number for that.
I don't know, maybe, maybe Danielle would have an idea there, or anyone else?
Okay.
Okay, that totally depends on practice to practice and a real audit must begin. Yeah.
Yeah.
You know, it truly does. You know, and and when when we're going through this transition with clients, you know, I typically say, brace yourself for at least a 30% reduction.
Okay.
Hmm.
If it's less than that, then it's a pleasant surprise. But 30% you you know is a safe net. If you're looking for that generalization.
Check. Thank you very much, Dominica. Just do. It's good to have a little benchmark to know, you know.
Of course! No, you definitely want to go in knowing on average.
What is?
There we go. Now, Ken, we have a question about the map. So, uh, Dr. Tom Server, a dentist, and Dr. Garnett, Jack are asking about, um… Where? So does this strategy for dropping Ppos change? If you are in a rural market versus a saturated urban city? Does the geography of the practice change the playbook for independence?
Okay.
I don't believe it does. And and and I say that specifically because ultimately it's up to you to build out the type of practice that you want to have. It's up to you to decide what modalities you're going to offer, and to the degree you're going to start to move away from insurance dependence. And, by the way, being rural.
Generally, it's a little bit easier, um, if you're in a rural setting to move over to less insurance dependence, because a lot of those patients aren't willing to travel as far, they're willing to maybe pay, you know, slightly higher fees as opposed to if, you know, they live in a very urban area where, you know, there are six dental practices within a walk, so to speak.
On the rural side, just naturally, it's gonna… it's… they're gonna… they're gonna get over the hurdle, uh, faster.
Hmm?
Okay, thanks, Ken. Now, Dominica, finally, we have a question on the negotiation logic from Paul.
Takamoto and Dr. Eddie Gutierrez. So do PPO companies ever actually have a strategic reason to raise fee schedules to keep high quality office in the network, or is the negotiation process usually a one-way street?
Where the insurance company holds all the cards.
You know, if you have multiple locations, or if you have a large patient base of that specific, you know, insurance company that you're serving a lot of their clients, and you have a high retention rate.
And you can prove that you've been in business for a really long time, then yes, there are PPO companies that can and will.
negotiate fees. I've had success rates of companies that we've successfully negotiated and seen a raise anywhere from 12% to 18% in, you know, without any in comparison to without any negotiations.
Okay, is 12 to 18%. Was that… Was that money just being left on the table if they didn't even try?
Correct, that was, you know, that dental practice has not evaluated their fees for more than 5 years. They have not done any kind of fee negotiation. So there was really opportunities for growth, and the Ri for the on their investment was well worth it.
Check, check. So one last question. Follow up there, Dominica. So what's a good.
timeframe for us to, you know, revisit these fees. You said they haven't looked at it for 5 years?
Most… so I would recommend, um, evaluating your fees on an annual basis. You know, you, when you're talking about overhead, your overhead climbs anywhere from, like I mentioned in my first question, anywhere from 3.
to 6% on an annual basis. So I would I would advise you to evaluate it on an annual basis. But in terms of fee negotiations, you wouldn't be able to negotiate fees more than between 2 or 3 years.
Check. Right. Here we go. Now, can a question for you. When a practice hires associates faster than it can train and support them properly. What's a pattern that you're seeing that shows up in how much it costs?
To run the practice versus what those providers are actually producing.
Yeah, sure. So, it's not uncommon for dentists and dental groups that are employing associate doctors. It's not uncommon for them to have at least a percentage, some percentage of their production.
to be part of their compensation. And then sometimes they might have a base fee or some… or something else like that. So to the degree you are hiring more doctors, and you do not have a way to utilize them, the ones who have some type of a base fee, that's just gonna eat right.
right into your overhead, into your cash flow. Um, and so you want to absolutely do everything you can to not over-hire during this process, and to keep yourself even a little safe if you did feel like you needed to hire some because you felt like it was going to be.
coming faster, at least have some of their compensation be variable-based as opposed to a fixed fee.
check a good compensation structure can align those problems. Now, Dominica, one last question for you here. What steps should a practice take to proactively educate its patient base on the benefits of receiving care outside of managed care pay PO plans.
So patients understand the value rather than focusing solely on the insurance participation.
Honestly, this is a question that I'm most glad you asked because I think that everything else we talked about today fails without it, and I think that Ken, at one point alluded to it. You know, you can negotiate better contracts. You can train your team, you can… Um, you know, instill the value, but if your patient base walks in every appointment believing that insurance participation is the defining measure of your value, you will always be fighting a rearguard action.
So dental insurances, dental insurance, and I say this over and over again until I'm blue in the face. I like wearing blue, so… but I want to say that dental insurance was never designed to cover comprehensive care.
It was designed as a benefit supplement. Typically capped at $1,000 to $2,000 a year, a number that hasn't changed meaningfully in 40 years.
So I will say that it is capped at $2,000 a year, and that benefit has not changed in 40 years, despite inflation.
Um, so, but patients have been conditioned by their employers, by HR departments, by insurance companies themselves, and frankly, by dentists to view insurance participation as the primary differentiator when choosing a provider.
Right.
The practice that wants to reduce Ppo dependence must actively work to reframe value away from, do you take my insurance towards the quality of care and experience they'll receive?
This isn't a sales exercise. It's truly an education mission that I took upon myself that I truly want to instill in every single dental practice that I touch. It should be embedded in every patient touchpoint.
Your website, the new patient call, any intake paperwork, the hygiene appointment, and as well as any and all follow-up communications. Your team needs to be trained on how to talk about it confidently.
And everybody and and your patients should feel the same message from the time they pick up that call, that phone to call you to the time that they're walking out the door into the parking lot after they receive treatment.
Right. Thank you very much for that wonderful reminder there, Dominica, that PPOs were not meant to cover comprehensive care. But you know, the thing that we really need to shift is the mindset to really understanding we are communicating the quality.
of care to our clients at each and every touchpoint we get.
Uh, with that being said, I would like to extend my gratitude to Ken and Dominica. Thank you for pulling back the curtain on the map for… for an independent and thriving practice, giving us the financial roadmap we can actually trust.
We will be moving on to the next segment here.
Okay. So…
Now we've seen the math, and we've seen the leaks.
But here's the hard truth. You can't stop relying on insurance until you start building your own influence. So if you aren't on the PPO list, you had to be the number one destination on Google ChatGPT, perplexity.
wherever the search goes. So you have to be the obvious choice in your zip code.
And that is why I'm excited to introduce our next speaker.
Naren Arul Raja. Naren is the founder and CEO of Echo Marketing, as well as a co-founder of the Reducing Insurance Dependence Academy.
He's the visionary when it comes to helping healthcare professionals thrive in a digital-first world. He doesn't just do marketing, he builds systems that provides the oxygen for PPO independent practices.
He's here to show you exactly how to replace those high-volume, low reimbursement patients with high-value ones who choose you for your expertise. Nair, the floor is yours for the anti-PPO marketing Q&A.
Thank you, Don, and I want to take a minute to thank all of our panelists, and of course all the attendees as the founder of this community. I do appreciate all of you for, you know, being part of it. We literally have, you know, more than 1,500 members now who are all.
in the process of dropping Ppo plans, and I'm very proud of the community and what we are doing as a group.
Today, I'm going to be answering a lot of the questions I get. It comes as emails. Sometimes people ask it in, you know, these kind of events, and even even for this event, we had, like, literally hundreds of questions that were sent in.
I'm going to focus on two primary themes, two types of questions I keep getting. One is, um.
Currently, my marketing is PPO. In other words, if I don't have these PPO plans, I'll be in big trouble. So, how do I change that? And how do I do it affordably? And we set a target of, can you grow your business while spending no more than 2% on marketing?
Mm-hmm.
So that's one theme that I'm going to be talking about. And the second theme is, you know, what about AI? Is AI affecting search? Is AI changing the way patients find me? And how do I respond as a practice owner? So I'm going to cover both. So hang in there. Don, if you don't mind, if you could ask the questions and I could.
Go into the answers, that would be, like, wonderful.
Yeah, absolutely. Absolutely. So the first question we got here for you is, why do PPO write-offs limit the growth of a typical dental practice?
Don't they help bringing new patients?
Yeah, that's an excellent question. If you look at the most most practices today across the Us. Around 90% of them have some type of PPO participation, and many of them are dependent on PPO. In other words.
If you take away VPOs, their practices. you know, will not do well. And doctors are afraid of that. So what happens is you become what I call a PPO practice. And a PPO practice is a practice where the number one question that the entire team, including the doctor, gets trained to.
workaround is, hey, is it covered by insurance? Because a lot of the patients, they might be having $200,000, $300,000 jobs, but when they are on that PPO plan, they think if it's not covered by insurance, that means the doctor is trying to sell them something they don't need. I'm not saying everyone is like that, but a vast majority is like that.
So the challenge with that is then you kind of end up with a team and a mindset that only does what's covered by insurance dentistry. So pretty much the bare minimum dentistry, not what got people excited to go to dental school.
In terms of beautiful smiles or changing lives. So, it has two kind of an effect. One is, you know, I'm sure you've heard the phrase, right? You become like the people you spend the most time with. So, if, you know, even 30-40% of your patients are PPO patients, and their first question is, is it covered? Is it covered?
And if it's not, it's almost like you're climbing a taking a rock up the hill. A lot of practice owners just give up even trying to present ideal dentistry. So the cost of PPO is not only like, hey, 30, 40, 50% of your production.
goes in the form of adjustments. In other words, your usual and customary fee minus, uh, all, you know, what you actually get paid. So let's say your usual and customer fee for a particular procedure is $1,000. You might, let's say you're getting paid $800. That means the adjustment is $700, and you multiply that by every patient visit.
With every PPO patient, so that's one problem, right? So you are now forced to run your business where your revenue is down 40%, but your expenses are the same. You don't get discounts on rent because you're a PPO practice, your team doesn't work for you for less money because you're a PPO practice.
Your supplies are not discounted because you're a PPO practice, so you're kind of, on one hand, really trying to do more with less, which means you're working harder, it's all about speed, you don't really get to enjoy the patient, you don't really get to build relationships. So that's one part of the challenge. The second is.
Like I said, you become institutionalized, you become this practice that gives up on ideal dentistry, that gives up on doing the things that got you excited when you were in dental school, that gives up on high-value services. So you kind of… become this lowest common denominator practice, and that can have, again, huge implications. So every year is harder than last year. Why? Expenses are always going up. I mean, it has been going up a lot since COVID. Like, a lot of expenses today versus 2021, at least 50-60% higher.
But the amount of revenue you're making as a practice hasn't kept up because insurance companies are not paying you 50, 60% more. So you are kind of getting squeezed. So I do think that's why the PPO model is a very limiting model. I'm not saying, you know, drop every PPO plan tomorrow and you're going to be okay. I'm saying.
Be smart, like, drop the worst one. It's the ones where you literally are losing money. Start with one, and then do the second one, and so forth. So slowly but surely, you're replacing this.
practice that is driven by low profit, low margin, high volume to high profit, high margin, enjoyable dental spray.
Check. Really getting out of that frame box of being a PPO practice into one that is much more.
aligned with high-value patient care. Now, uh, Naren, is it really possible for a dental practice to grow while spending less than 2% on marketing? Uh, how is that different from PPOs?
Yeah, absolutely. You know, we have been doing this from 2007, and many of our practice owners spend 1%, 2% of their revenue in marketing. Some even spend half a percent. And we have seen this time and again. I'll tell you the secret. See, at the end of the day.
Healthcare is very personal to most people, even the ones who are on a PPO plan. So usually they'll start by Googling whatever they're interested in. Let's say I have a toothache, I Google it, or I want veneers, I Google it. And then I go to the website, I look at the different options available, I look at maybe a few websites, and then I.
spend some time getting to know different options. And then finally, I look at the reviews, and then I pick up the phone and call, and that phone experience is, again, exceptional. And then I book the appointment. So that's kind of the flow that people go through, even the ones on a PPO plan, because it's a… the obvious sign that they don't even know that.
You take that PPO, because the very first question they ask is, do you take this PPO plan? So really, they're going to Google and figuring things out. So in my experience, if you if you build a marketing campaign that's organic, meaning SEO, Google SEO driven, you can definitely spend less than 2%. We have literally 400 dental practices we work with.
And the thing that I'm most proud of is, unlike other marketing companies, our clients, 90% of them stay with us year after year, which means they're getting the best ROI of anything out there, because SEO is a really low-cost way to attract ideal patients. You can also do Google Ads, but then your budget won't be less than 2%. It might be more like 5-10%.
Why Google Ads? Google has to make more money every year, they're making $250 billion from ads in the last year. So what that means is the cost of an ad continues to go up and up and up, you know, and the second part of it is people know it's an ad, so you need a lot more people.
To get a quality patient to come into the door. A lot of people will not know Sho, you know, so you just need more volume at a very high cost. So Google Ads is the second best option, but you can't control your cost to less than 2% with Google Ads. But definitely, if you want something quick, like, let's say you're a startup and you're okay with spending.
You know, 10% of your revenue or your projected revenue, then of course Google Ads would be a good choice. Now, PPO plans, on the other hand, are spending 40%, right? What I mean is, if you're making $1,000… if you're producing $1,000 worth of dentistry and you're only collecting 600.
that adjustment, which is, yes, the… you didn't write a marketing check, but pretty much the impact is still the same. Like, you're only… you're giving up $400 for every $1,000 of dentistry you do because of the PPO adjustment. So, compared to 40%, both of these are good, like 2% on organic versus.
10% on Google Ads, but I definitely think if you're going to be practicing for, you know, a few more years, at least, let's say 2, 3, 5, 10 years, you want to keep it as low as possible. So I really think you should benchmark it at 2% of your revenue, and that should be the maximum you should be spending on all your marketing.
Okay, now there is an interesting distinction you made there, Naren, with regards to high quality patients. So can a CEO help our practice owners get higher quality patients, perhaps like implant cases?
What about the non-PPO patients?
Yeah, that's a great question. A lot of people who are willing to pay money out of their own pocket, they don't care about PPO, right? Like, they have decided they're going to get a beautiful smile. They have decided to find the best solution. They have planned it in their budget, like, they want to spend 10, 20, 30,000 instead of going on that vacation.
buying their car, they want to get that smile. They are not going to their regular dentist, the PPO dentist, and saying, you know, I have $30,000, can I give it to you? Instead, what they do is they go and look online if it's Invisalign, they'll start learning about Invisalign and who are the different providers for Invisalign. If it's sedation, because they have a lot of dentistry, or if it's implants.
The example you brought up, they are going to start looking for those things. They'll start typing in implant dentist near me, implant before and after. So they're looking for all kinds of information to educate themselves on what their options are. And it's no different when they are redoing their kitchen. Like, they start looking for different options.
So when they start looking for these options, you want to show up again and again for at least 30, 40 different keywords related to implants. So, for example, dental implant, you know, city name, dental implant zip code, it could be zirconia implant. They may have heard of the word zirconia, or different types of implants.
You know, so when they are starting to look for these things, are you showing up? That's number one. You can show up through ads, they know it's an ad and it's a lot more expensive, so I wouldn't recommend it. And also, like I already alluded to, like, the click-through rates and the conversion rate is going to be a lot lower because they know it's an ad, so they don't… They don't give you the benefit of the doubt, they're always looking at you with suspicion when they find you through ads. So show up for at least 30 to 40 keywords related to implants near the top of Google search results. Now, I'm going to touch on this later on about AI search. Now, search.
Everywhere is AI powered. Ai is integrated into Google. Of course, you can't ignore Gemini and, you know, ChatGPT and Perplexity, the top three AI search engines, in addition to Google. And I'll get to that. So you want to make sure, doesn't matter where they're searching, you keep showing up. That's number one.
Now, second thing is they have to go to the right page. So if I Google something to do with implants, don't take me to your home page, get me to the page that talks about implants. And when I go there, I should see before and after pictures, maybe some cases. I should see maybe a welcome video making me kind of get to know who you are, and.
How long you have been helping patients… Implants, so really helping me, you know, like your practice, like you as a dentist, and of course, give me the proof that you are really good at what you said you are. Those are the cases, and so forth. And then finally, you know, Google reviews. Like, I'm going to still go and type in, you know, your practice name and reviews, or your practice name, and I'm going to start reading up reviews. Are you getting high-quality 5-star paragraph reviews?
If you do these 3 things, meaning you are crushing SEO, you are dominating it, like, our clients, uh, every single one within a year are ranking for at least 100 or more keywords and phrases on top of Google search results. Many of our clients are even ranking, you know, for 300, 400.
If anyone wants to see the kind of outcomes we can produce, just type your name, we will, you know, maybe share that information with you, or, like, have a meeting to really address your concerns or your questions. So that's where I would start. I would focus on, like, dominating Google.
Optimizing the landing pages with cases and videos, and then finally focusing on the Google reviews. That's where I would recommend at least 10 or more reviews every single month.
Check. Now let's get into that AI, since you know it seems to be everywhere these days. So more practice owners are really inquiring about AI. Now you've mentioned doctors reaching out and.
Asking if SEO is dead or saying Google's update have hurt their rankings. What's really happening, Naren?
That's an excellent question. Google, we all know, was not the very first company to release the AI tool that we all are familiar with. The very first company to release the AI tool was ChatGPT, which is OpenAI. Openai was a… Nonprofit created by Elon Musk in response to Google was the only game in town that was, like, going crazy on AI almost 10 years ago. So Elon Musk woke up and said, we don't want a world where Google kind of controls AI and everybody else is just clueless.
So he created this nonprofit, and of course, then he broke off from it, and he created his own, you know, own AI company called XAI. Anyways, and then, of course, you have Anthropic, which is another AI company, and of course, Google itself.
is the first and the oldest AI company. If you look at 2025, Google's stock price doubled. So they went from around $2 trillion to $4 trillion, and that's because… because Google has a lot to lose when something goes wrong. Like, for example, we all heard of hallucination.
I'm sure we have all heard of, you know, several people suing OpenAI for their kids getting, you know, committing suicide because ChatGPT talked them into, you know, taking a gun and shooting themselves in the head, because it didn't know that… it was just talking to them, you know, remember, this is not a human being, this is a machine, and it didn't know the implications of what it was saying, and, like, several people like Texas, there was a case of a young.
College graduates. So anyway, so… but Google couldn't take those kind of chances, because remember, it's going to be on main page, headline news all over the world, and, you know, they're going to be in big trouble. So they were very slow coming out of it, but last year, they really doubled down. Today, if you look at Google Search.
12 billion times a day, Google Regular Search is being used. And of that, more than a billion times a day, it's what they call AI overview. So, for example, if you type in a query like dental implant cost in Chicago, or any city name.
Google will go and study all the different options in Chicago for dental implants, and it'll give you, like, a paragraph or an essay of, hey, these are the kind of implant options you can consider, and here are the price ranges in the city of Chicago, and it'll give you 3 or 4 different websites to refer from.
So now AI is just built into Google. The advantage Google has is it has users, right? It has 12 billion times a day people using it. Now, when you compare that to ChatGPT, they have 800 million in a whole month. They share weekly and monthly stats versus Google shares.
daily style. And also, of those 800 million, 700 million are coming from outside of North America, so a lot of overseas traffic. So, inside the US, they don't have that much volume, at least as compared to Google. So Google, for example, grew their search volume by 15%, so that 12 billion number.
You know, it used to be around 10 billion, now it's 12 billion. So literally, Google grew by 2 billion when these other guys, you know, their entire volume is 800 million. So Google really came back with a vengeance. They integrated, you know, AI into their regular search. So they have both AI overview and AI mode. Now, in addition to that, you don't know, even though the challenge that every other company has, and this is the same problem.
Why they try to break up Microsoft 25 years ago when Netscape was, you know, coming up with the Internet? Just, they're so big. So it doesn't matter how much the new guy tries, just because they are already controlling 90, 95% of the market, it's impossible for the new guys to penetrate, especially on the consumer side.
Of course, the other thing that happened for Google is with the Trump administration, they kind of settled all the antitrust cases against Google. So Google is scot-free and pretty much Google is back to doing what it always does, which is dominate the world. So I think you need to focus on Google a lot, and I'll talk about how to do that.
But at the same time, with our clients, we also focus on perplexity, Gemini, and ChatGPT. So we look at two things when it comes to these three other search engines. One is how many times are you showing up? Like I said, with Google, we want to show up at least 100 or more keywords every single client.
You know, at the top of Google search results, and some are, like, 300, 400. With ChatGPT and Perplexity and Gemini, we want the same thing. We want our clients to show up for dozens and dozens of keywords and phrases. Now, if I were to compare apples to apples when it comes to dentistry and how patients are finding dentists.
Google is still 98% of the market. These other things are combined maybe 2% to 3% of the market. So I think in case these AI search engines grow, you don't want to take any chances. So you want to dominate both. So that's my advice. Now, how do you do that when it comes to Google?
I think there's a couple of things you have to really pay attention to is.
Google doesn't like AI written content. So if you have content that's written by AI, you're going to get penalized. So you still need humans, you still need all the guidelines Google is, you know, recommending in terms of content. And also Google is Google made a fundamental shift to how it looked at.
What's a good website? In the old days, they had something called, um… Google Lighthouse call, which is a score they gave every single page. Now they replaced it with something called Google CRUX. That's CR for Chrome, UX for user interface. So it's like, pretty much they're looking at everything from the point of view of a Chrome user, whether it's on a desktop or whether it's on a mobile device. And if that Chrome user as a whole likes that website, they like the website. So what does it mean? So Google talks about.
you know, trying to be helpful, trying to have lots of content, trying to organize information the way Google recommends.
Another thing that they really, really look at, because a lot of people are using AI content which Google hates is EEAT, which means adding your particular experience, your particular expertise, and all your qualifications and authoritative information like, hey, you are the president of this group, or.
You have a degree from this university, like, properly in the form of a bio, that really, really is helping, especially in healthcare. So many of our clients, after AI happened, especially in last year, instead of ranking for 100 or 150 keywords, all of a sudden are now ranking for 300, 400 keywords.
So we saw the people who were already leaning into, like, you know, working on content, following all of Google's rules. Like, in our company, we have 14 teams, and 9 of them are just focused on Google and making Google happy. So all of a sudden, the people who are really, like, playing an A++ game when it comes to all aspects of what Google care about.
are now getting double or triple the traffic. The other ones who were kind of doing a little bit are getting killed. So it's like the strong are getting stronger, and the weak, or the average are just getting assassinated. So, uh, I think if you're willing to lean in, and if you're willing to take the long term, and you have the right partner to really, really dominate.
This you're gonna do fine. So I think focus on EAT as new things and see our UX. Of course, NAP, still important. Google, you know, quality backlinks still important. Original content, human content, still important. So a lot of the fundamental things that the Google cared about before are still important.
But CRUX and EAT are like the new additions. And the other thing is Google is now changing really fast. And so it used to always change fast, but it's getting faster and faster. So you have to keep up. So what used to work a month ago may not work today. What Google told you to do a month ago?
You may have to redo it because now Google has updated standards. So I think AI is an opportunity to lean in like coming back, you know, we had a client, I had a call with a client recently, you know, he's getting 80 new patients. He's a $5 million practice, and he wants to get to $6 million. Right. And and he was looking at, you know, other companies and they were, you know, quoting him literally like 25, $30,000 a month.
In marketing, and he's spending, like, a fraction of that with us. So, like, you really don't have to waste money on marketing. Like, you know, like a lot of marketing companies would say, spend 5-10% of revenues. I really think 2% is a good number, and if you do it well, you can even keep it at 1%.
I really think, you know. Foundation should be a CEO. Then on top of that, have good landing pages, and then on top of that, have Google reviews. Google reviews is something you have to work on. But if you do these 3 things, and you really, like, pay attention to how many keywords am I ranking for, how many phone calls am I getting.
You should track it. By the way, put a call tracking number. One of the other things we do is we listen to calls, and we provide feedback on how many calls are getting missed, how many are booking, how many are not booking, because.
Imagine you have an awesome marketing, but your team is not trained or not supported properly, so they're only booking 1 out of 3 new patients. By the way, the average dental practice in the US is only booking 1 out of 3 new patients. So you want to work on all these things. If you do, you're going to do really well.
Right. So, Aaron, for our practice owners listening in, what what is the first step that you would recommend they take to really change the trajectory for growth in 2026?
Yeah, I think are you ranking for every keyword under the sun? You should be ranking for 100 or more. If not, I recommend booking a marketing strategy meeting. And what we do in that marketing strategy meeting, we'll put a link here. We look at you and your competition, and we'll tell you.
kind of like report card, like a health card. Like, you think of it like an annual checkup. It will tell you, hey, are you crushing it or you are not crushing it? If you're ranking for 100 or more keywords, don't change a thing, just keep doing what you're doing. If you're not, then… you know, what are the root causes? Is it EEAT? Is it like, you know, is it CRUX? We'll tell you what the root causes are. And also, we'll look at you on the AI search engines, both Google and the other ones. Are you showing up there? Are you, you know, doing well there? We'll also look at your competition. If your competition is.
Like doing a lot better, what are they doing uniquely that you're not doing? So SEO is the front end of the funnel. And then, of course, we look at the landing pages. Are those landing pages compelling enough for somebody to want to pick up the phone and call you? They are not, what are the changes you need to make? And finally, like, you know.
All the other, you know, leading indicators, like your nap, your Lighthouse, all the other things that are driving these things. So we look at, like, are there any nap issues? Are there any, you know, original content issues? Are there any duplicate content issues where some marketing company, unfortunately.
90% of marketing companies use the same information for all their clients, so they copy-paste. Google hates that kind of stuff. So are they… are you accidentally doing things that's hurting you? And of course.
When we take on a client in the first two months, we put, like, around 200 hours worth of work, cleaning up a lot of the mess that.
you know, needs to be cleaned up. And then we are putting minimum 30 hours a month.
And our fee, I'll disclose it, it's 1250… $50 a month, it's all inclusive. And it includes social media, call tracking, SEO, websites, everything. We never send an extra bill. It's all included. And that should cover most practices. Of course, once you work with us for an year and you have like some of our other clients, like a big ambition, you want to get to 2 million, 3 million, 4 million, 5 million.
I still think benchmark it at 2%, so if you want to get to 2 million, then maybe, you know, have a $40,000 marketing budget, which is still, you know, a lot less than what a lot of other companies are recommending. I really think if you do it right, 2% is all you need to do well with marketing.
Check. So, to all our attendees, really, you have unlocked this fantastic resource. Do make the best use of it. The link has been dropped in the chat box there. Something, uh… Perhaps a way to think about, um, a resource like this is if you do attend it, what are you risking? Honestly, it'll just be your time when you go to the virtual marketing strategy meeting, it'll just be your time. There's no comment commitments whatsoever. But.
What if you don't? Right? As Naren mentioned, you might be missing out on a great resource that'll help you elevate your practice to the next level and beyond. So do make the best use of it. It'll be time well spent.
Uh, with that being said, Naren, thank you so much for.
sharing those insight. Go ahead.
Absolutely. Thank you, Naren, for really showing us how to stop chasing insurance lists and start building the digital influence that's driving true, sustainable growth.
Now, then, uh…
Right.
Now Naran has showed us how to ensure that your practice is the only destination patients see online. But once that phone rings, once that patient steps into your lobby.
The operations begin. So here is the radar reality. If you aren't on the insurance list, your patient experience has to be so exceptional that the cost becomes secondary to care. You had to move your practice from being.
Hmm.
Am I stuck? Okay, I think I'm moving, but… PC is frozen.
Yeah. Some days. PCs freeze.
And, uh, issues just pop out of nowhere. My apologies for that.
We are going to do something very exciting over here. We are going to get into the operations side of the question. Now, to do that, we have Dr. Michael Sonic. Dr. Sonic, uh… Can you give us a self-introduction real quickly?
Sure. I'm a full-time periodontist practicing in Fairfield, Connecticut for over 40 years, and I'm an academician teach at NYU, University of Connecticut, and Yale written 7 books, but my true passion is really teaching and educating and.
after being out of dental school for a number of years. I move. I still do clinical work a couple of days a week, but my true passion is improving the quality of the interaction between the healthcare provider.
And the consumer, which is the patient. And my book is called Treating People, Not Patients, which is all about changing the healthcare experience, giving people really positive experience.
Yeah, absolutely. And let's really dive into what that looks like here in this panel. Dr. Sonic, thank you so much for being here. It's a pleasure to have you here.
Thank you, John.
Right. And next up we do have Daniel Kramer. Daniel, if you don't mind a little bit of an introduction there.
Yeah, of course. I am a practice consultant, been in dentistry for over 20 years now, and I focus on not just the practice, but the people in the practice, because without working through them, our practices don't usually have.
success. So, um, I'm the people coach, is what I like to say. Happy to be here with you guys.
Wonderful. It's great to have you here, Danielle. And I do apologize, uh, my PC was frozen just a little bit ago, hence why I requested the assistance of our panelists for the introductions.
Now, uh, let's get into the main Q&A here. Dr. Sonic, when a practice invests heavily in clinical skills, but leaves the money conversation to chance at the front desk.
What pattern do you consistently see play out?
no closure. You know the cases don't close. People don't say yes to treatment.
No closure.
And people leave without. you know, scheduled the appointment. And I guess the previous speaker said that, you know, out of three people that call the office, only one makes an appointment or one goes through a treatment.
Um, so we look at case acceptance as a very important part, you know, in a good.
It's a good number to look at, you know, an important indicator of practice health growth. Mine is actually a little high, and some people say mine is too high, because I have a 90% case acceptance.
And just to give you some, our practice is at over $5 million practice. I produce close to $15,000 a day, working 2 days a week.
And I have a 90% case acceptance and a 4-month waiting list to come into our practice.
Uh, and that's not because I'm a good surgeon. You know, there are plenty of good surgeons out there. It's because I could connect with the people that are there. And that connection is not me. By the time a patient sees me in the practice and comes into my operatory.
I sort of have to blow it for them not to say yes. It's already set up, you know, the office where it's located, what it looks like, the address, the lawn, the people, what it smells like.
You know, how they're treated from the website. We've talked a lot before about the website, what that looks like, the social media, you know, etc. And so I have the… advantage of being in the same location for 42 years. So that's good and bad for a surgeon. I mean, you see the problems, but you also see your successes. So, oftentimes, a lot of practices, the handoff is not done well. So there's really no handoff of the patient. It's just a continuum where the patient comes in, they're sort of ushered through the treatment.
And it's sort of seamless. And we have a whole system to do that. And since I've written the book, which I wrote during COVID, because I was really just taught mostly clinical.
I sort of looked at everything that we did and I sort of did it unconsciously. I was unconsciously competent.
Um, and what I've looked at is why do people say yes? And I've looked at the touch points along the way of how that happens. And it's actually become a system. And we talk about that in the books and, you know, my videos and everything else that I, that I, that I do.
How did you figure out that you were unconsciously competent, and what was, like, you know, the moment that you had that revelation that you need to… become more aware of it.
Yeah, my my coach. So I I I'm trained in neuro-linguistic programming, which is sort of a soft science. It's how we connect. You know, it's we basically connect with our senses, right? You know, touch, sight.
Hearing, smelling, you know. smell, all of that. And when we talk with patients, it's mostly what they see, what they hear.
You know, it's not smell, it's usually not touched too much. It shouldn't be. It's really what they see and what they hear. That's mostly it. And I was, you know, one of my coaches was in my office. He was busy with me. He needed an implant.
And he watched me talk and he said to me, he goes, you're unconsciously competent. And I didn't really understand that you could be.
unconsciously incompetent, which a lot of people are in the world. They just don't even know they're not doing it. And then you can be incompetent, but you know you're not doing a very good job, and you really want to.
Or you can be unconsciously competent, which I was. And then you can be consciously competent. So you want to have a con… you want to be conscious of what it is to, you know, be competent, whether it's, you know, in patient interactions or flying a jet plane, you really want your pilot.
You know, when you're flying from Detroit to Austin, you know, be consciously competent of how to fly that plane. You know, I was like, hey, I do a pretty good job, and I crash every now and then. So I actually started to look at that system.
Hmm.
And his name is John O'Connor. He says, you're really good. He goes, you just don't know why you're good. And so after he was there, we started to break it down, and I've done some teaching with him, and I started to look at everything that I did or do. And I still do, because sometimes it works really well, Don, you know, like I'm talking.
You like tonight, you know, something's worked really well, some things they didn't. I think it's in the air today, because I came home last night, I flew in from Atlanta, I got home at midnight, and I'm in New York, and our Internet was out. It took us about 8 hours to fix it. So we got that going, and now I'm on my laptop because my computer won't start here.
And so I normally have a couple screens go, so that's that's out today. And then you've had some practical problems today, too. And so how do you handle that? You know, when things going badly, how do you handle those things? So I've tried to get really good about handling the problems, and we all have them. They're every day. Every day we have them.
Because everyone's watching you. They're watching all the time.
So these good questions.
Absolutely. Absolutely, uh, Dr. Sonic. So you figured out your.
areas of improvement, and then ensure that translated into a seamless system.
And the outcome of it, 90% case acceptance.
Yes, hi. I mean, I'm doing. I mean, I'm always. I'm a constant learner. It's almost everybody on this. Most dentists are most people. I know everybody on the panel. We're all high achievers and constant learners. We always want to get better. And so, like, there's 5… 4 or 5 things now I'm trying to get better, better at.
One of them is AI, you know, social media to an extent. You know, I do a lot more teaching now than I ever have. How can I teach better? And because what I'm teaching is really hard to teach. It's very easy for me to teach you how to do an implant or a bone graft or a gingival graft. I mean, I just show you how to do it.
And everyone wants to do it because they want to learn how to do the procedures because they think if they do the procedures, they'll make more money. But that's not the case.
Right.
you know, you won't make more money if you learn more procedures. You know, you make more money if you do the procedures well and you treat the people really well and you do it without being manipulative, and… That's very hard to teach, you know?
Okay.
I don't know if it's even possible to teach, but I have not given up.
Absolutely.
Yeah. Yeah.
That's what we like to hear, and hopefully along our conversation here tonight, that's exactly what we are trying to communicate to our attendees. Now, Danielle, when a practice stops leading with what insurance covers and starts leading with what the treatment is actually worth.
What shift do you see in how patients respond?
Yeah, so we're sort of talking about value. over insurance. It's interesting. I didn't necessarily know what this meant until I.
That's right.
had walked all the steps in dentistry for a lot of years, but I think that value in treatment means a lot of different things in what we do. It's not just the dollar value, but it's also the worth of what it is to that patient.
And I think those things are conveyed from the very first, like the very first encounter with that patient. So just like doctor just went over, it is like that first encounter with that patient. It's building that trust that.
when they come in and we give that treatment plan to them. They understand right away the value of that versus even needing to go over the dollars and cents of a insurance. What is my insurance going to cover?
And I think it's so important because we start to understand the difference between a patient that's gonna talk to us like that versus the shopper, right? We all know who the shoppers are as our patients.
And we have to be really confident in our space. We have to understand and be educated on how to talk to people. And that's another thing I didn't know in the beginning. My education is on behavioral health.
So it wasn't until and I talk about this a lot when I speak, it wasn't until I connected those dots where I was like, why is there a disconnection in.
This treatment, the patient needs, the value of this treatment to that patient and why they're so concerned over the dollars and cents. They need this. They need it to be healthy.
And it was when I finally broke through what that was, and it was the connection with us in the office and the patient.
that there was so much movement, and it felt like we weren't really hearing no anymore. We were… the patients were understanding, they were… and just, like, that 90%, I can almost say in all of my client offices, we get that same response, because we're talking to the patient about the value.
And again, it's not just the dollar value, it's the value to the patient on what that treatment's gonna be.
Daniel, can you give us an example?
Um, yeah, so, well, I guess elaborate a little bit. Example on which part?
how you're communicating value as a 90%er versus someone who is not converting as much.
Yeah. Again, I think it's that the relationship between our teams and our patients. So when we're talking to patients about treatment, it's it's not just that dollar value. So when I go to a patient and I say, hey.
you know, this is the treatment that doctors diagnose for you. It's going to be really important that we finish this. I know how you're feeling. I've been in these shoes before with you. Let's walk down this like I want to walk down this path with you.
But I've already built trust with them before I even sit in that seat and talk to them as a as a Tc. My team has built trust on that initial phone call. They understand where the the insurance sits in our practice and how it's working in our practice versus.
The treatment that's going to be explained to them. So when we do walk down that conversation that has to do with.
you know, treatment value dollars. They're already committed. They hear the confidence in the team, and there's really not any question on, is my doctor right? Does the team know what they're giving to me?
they're really… they're committed to the yes, because they understand and they trust the team that they're with.
check. So trust is already billed the clinic as a brand. That's where we are going with. Is that correct, Danielle?
Correct, yeah.
Uh, so, Dr. Sonic, when you can clearly trace which marketing effort brought a patient through the door, what's your rule for deciding where to keep spending?
It's a good question because we I'm not a marketing genius. What we do is we do some really basic things. We just are most of our marketing is internal. It's patients.
And I've been, you know, when I started practice in 1985, no one was marketing. You know, I built it organically and I get with now today with marketing. The purpose of marketing is just to get people into the door so that you can present the care to them so that they can buy from you.
So I don't spend much on marketing right now. We do have a we do. I am on social media. But I've done that mostly for my younger partners and younger associates. The marketing comes in the way we just present ourselves. It's really starts before I even meet a patient. It's the referrals.
And you wonder, well, I give people really good care so that they refer others to you. Like, I don't want people to ever think about me when they're eating, but if somebody breaks a tooth that they know, I want them to think about me. They go, yeah, I had that same problem, they come in. So we really want to give them those.
What we call a WOW experience. And the marketing starts, you know, it could be the website, it could be social media, it could be they know somebody. It really starts when they first call our office and when they look at our website. So we have a… website, it's pretty much a masterclass in building a site. We have over 1,400 pages. It's all my own material, and every week we're building it. So we're constantly teaching, constantly educating. And it starts with our core values, which are educating. So we always educate our patients.
Hmm.
I always commit to them that I'm there for them for the rest of their lives so that we can get them healthy and keep them healthy. And we're very serious in what we do. It's not about selling the case, it's about getting them healthy. And we tell every patient at their first visit, we're going to do 3 things for them. We're going to get them healthier. We're going to improve their aesthetics, we're going to improve function.
We also tell them if they're in the right place because probably about 8 or 10% of our patients have severe dental phobia, and almost nobody likes being there. Very few people like to come in.
Well, in our practice, people say, we like coming here. It's just like a spa, but relax because we're very nice to them. So there's a lot of different touch points of marketing. There are probably about 20 before I even meet the patient.
And I don't think social media is the most important, because there's a lot of noise out there, and everybody is clamoring, you know, for those patients. As I'm building my teaching business more, and I'm doing more educating, you know, everybody has their own teaching center. Like, I've been teaching implants for 35 years, and I was one of the first to have a teaching center.
Now, I don't do as much in my practice, but there's 250 implant teaching centers in the United States, so everybody's the expert, so everybody's the best dentist in town.
And I don't think you need a tremendous number of patients, you just need a number of patients that really respect and care about what you're doing. You know, you don't want to compete on price. You really don't want to compete at all. I don't look at other dentists as my competition. I don't look at anybody as my competition. If I give really good value.
It seems to work. And but it won't be overnight. You can't really make it overnight success. Not a strong one. You can be successful quickly, but you really won't have the same type of death. You won't have roots, you know?
I really like the analogies in that especially with regards to, you know, you want to be the person that patients are thinking of when they do break a tooth.
And not necessarily when they're meeting.
Yeah. Nobody. Nobody has no one would ever say to you, Don, you know, go to my dentist. Why is he goes cheap.
It's really cheap dentist.
That's right. That's right. That's a whole, uh, mindset shift from a PPO practice to one that is focused on high-quality care of treatment and patients.
It's giving people value. You know, one of my mentors says, you have to care more about the value that you give than the money you receive.
And I don't ever not do treatment because of money. I always find a way to make it go within their budget. Now I won't lower my quality. I might do it over a longer period of time.
Hmm.
Yeah.
We have something that we do in our practice. It's, I mean, every practice should do it. Did you know that 90% of all practices don't do a comprehensive examination on their patients? That's pretty easy, you know? My daughter, who's a dentist, just bought a practice, and she's doing, and they didn't do comprehensive examinations.
And within five weeks. She's swamped, and the practice wasn't that busy, but she's there just doing comprehensive exam, and they didn't want to pay for it, because 90% of her patients take insurance. So she bought a practice that's insurance-based in a great community in a small.
It's boutique practice that she's creating within 5 weeks, she's given away free exams, free X-rays to everybody. And guess what? The return on that investment is tremendous. And now they they new equipment. I've watched it. Of course, she's my daughter, so I've trained her in this, you know, techniques.
And I've watched it work very quickly. So yeah.
Amazing. I hope the practice owners listening in can take that and try it out. Something to really consider.
Okay. Yeah, I was about to say 90% of all practices don't do a comprehensive exam, don't take x-rays, don't do periodontal probing.
There's a lot of work out there. And the United States, you know, 90% of the periodontal treatment, I mean, the periodontal disease is not being diagnosed. Only about 3% of the people get treatment. It's an epidemic.
Yeah.
Absolutely. Now, Danielle, the moment a caller asks, do you take my insurance? What needs to happen in the next 90 seconds to turn that call into a booked appointment?
Well, first, let's talk about what is happening, because I think it's important to talk about the stuff that is happening that's deterring patients, or it's getting the patients into the practices that the doctors then say, I don't want these patients here.
But our front office team members are essentially letting them in because they're transactional, and that's the only way to describe those phone calls is the patient is calling with an initial concern, and they've put insurance. Do you accept my insurance plan?
On top of that initial concern, because they know that something could cost money, and they don't know how much. So they want to understand right away when they call, is this going to be taken care of? Now, I personally feel like insurance is and I explain it to a lot of my clients that insurance is sort of like a discount plan.
We're just going to get $1,000 a year, and then the rest is going to come out of pocket, so let's learn to love it. And that's how I throw it out into the world. I'm very nonchalant about it, and most of my clients are like, all right, you're spot on. That's really what it is. And I think that in the dental industry, we've gone the extreme opposite of trying to teach.
everyone their insurance versus teaching our team members not to be transactional.
So within that first 90 seconds, we have really got to earn the trust of the patient. We're going to acknowledge the fact that that was a major concern. That's the first thing they asked us. So we're certainly going to answer the question, do we accept your plan? We accept all major PPO plans.
Hmm.
That's the truth. Are we in network with all of them? No, we're going to be a non-preferred provider, but we can accept that, and we're going to bill for you, and this is how it's going to work. Now we're going to redirect the phone call. We want to understand what the value is that they're looking for. Why are they calling us? Were they referred? Are they in pain?
What can I do to support what you're calling me for? How can I help you? And I think once we start to build that trust, start to edify our team, teach this caller how wonderful our providers are and our team members, now we've sort of made insurance.
No.
Secondary. They've asked us the question, we've answered it, but we've made the insurance question really secondary to everything else that we've just taught them about our practice. But that 90 seconds is… it's… It's everything to that initial call into the practice, and we've got to really build our team members up to understand how to handle that.
Right? So what you're saying is basically don't be giving out answers, but rather focus on building trust.
I think we give the answer right? We do have to be transparent about how we accept insurance in our space. But we also need to be building that relationship from the start with our practice. If we're not doing that, then what are we doing?
And again, I go back to I listen in a lot of phone calls and I travel into a lot of offices weekly. And those conversations are so transactional. And then the flip side is… How did I get here with these patients? How? Why don't they understand what our philosophy is and what our culture is that we're trying to build? And when we go back and sort of replay with that initial, you know, encounter was, it's right there. It was right there on that initial phone call, right where we had the opportunity to build that relationship with the patient.
So it's on that initial 90 seconds when that phone call happens and that one question that we all hate in dentistry happens, but we can divert and we can start to redirect and we can teach value right from that question.
Thank you very much, Daniel, for that answer. Dr. Sonic, in the 1st 90 days after a staff training, what's the one behavior you watch for that tells you whether patients are actually going to start saying yes more?
Well, it's not like we hire somebody. upon the patients.
Because we already have the culture. So when we hire somebody, I think what you're asking is, how do you know when you hire somebody, they get it?
That's fine.
You know, because my team has it. I have 25 people in our practice, and I'd hire all of them again. And that's rare. And we've had people there, you know, some of them have been there a couple of years, some of them in there 25 years. It's all over the place. So we have a very strong culture of people who are, and Danielle said it, you know, we talked about it all the time.
We don't want transactional relationships. We want transformative relationships. And then she says 90 seconds. I use that rule all the time. It's really not even 90 seconds, it's like 10 seconds. It's like that. The phone is very hard, though, to make that… to have a relationship, because you don't… you don't get to see.
what they look like and how they're responding. Um, so how do I know if they get it? Well, it all starts in the hiring process. And that's a, that's a whole, that's a whole different topic, but I'll quickly give it to you because it's a big problem that people have. They, they hire anybody to fill spots because we don't have many people that want to work right now. People that want to go to work, they want to work from home.
COVID sort of changed that a lot. So I don't care what business that you're in in the country, and I'm all over the country, people say, I can't find people. Well, I can find them, but I don't have, like, 50 people a week that I would hire. I go through.
This is going to sound crazy. 300 to 400 people before I hire anybody. So it's very hard to get a job in our practice. And we need people. We need 3 people now, and my partner called me up today, says someone's going to 3 days a week for 4, because I want you to hire this person.
And I didn't like her. I didn't think she'd fit. You know, I knew… I knew within 10 seconds of meeting her, she made me very anxious, and she made me anxious to make her a patient anxious. I didn't want to hire her. And he told me to hire somebody else that was one of his patients.
And I didn't like her either. I didn't think she was good. And we hired her and we tried to make her fit our culture. It doesn't work that way. You can't change people. And she was with us for, like, 5 months, and she pretty much.
brought the karma down in the office. We're working so hard to work with her, and she just, you know, she quit. I very rarely fire anybody. People usually just leave, but I never really have people quit, because by the time I hire somebody, they're the right fit. How do we figure out what the right fit client is? Well, you have to understand your culture, and you have to know what you're doing. You have to be very clear, and like you would say, conscious. I'm very conscious of my culture.
We have five core values. You know, we're team-hearted, you know, we're good servants, we're good to each other, okay? We're educational, we're health-oriented. Okay, we're really all work very, very hard together, and everyone knows what our core values are. They all know what our mission statement is, to improve the quality of patients' lives.
To give everybody a WOW experience. We don't have a dental practice. We have a spa. We happen to do dentistry in our spa, okay? It's a healthcare practice that we improve lives. That's where everybody is. So how do I know if they're going to work out?
They're gone… I don't even hire them. My team does. We do we do a resume, we do a culture index, which is which is something that tells us what their personality is. We do a FaceTime interview. They come in for a blink interview. If that works out, they spend a half day, then it's been the full day. We have so many touch points. And then at the end, my staff is the one that says.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, I like this person and I'm fighting with my partner. I'm not fighting with him because we're going to be really short staffed this summer. I just don't want to bring in this person. And I might just bring her in just to prove that don't, don't bring in the wrong people because you really want to hire slow and fire fast, as they say.
And when someone comes in, we know immediately, I know immediately if they're going to work at our practice. And people who are going to want to work here want to work at our practice, because they've read our website, they see what we do, they understand what we do. We have almost a thousand Google reviews. Now, we've written 7 books, you know, I mean, we're like a well-known practice in the area.
But I wasn't wasn't 40 years ago. My first year in practice, I grossed $35,000 with 90,000 overhead and forged thousand debt in 1985.
You know, went bankrupt a few years after that, you know, blew it all up. People go, you're so successful. How come you're so successful? I said, because I've made every mistake in the book.
You know, and it really comes down to four words. Be nice to people. Forget your marketing strategy. Just be really nice for people. Be honest. That's your niche. Be comprehensive. Treat the patients that it's the golden rule. It's so basic.
It's so easy. It's like, you know, how many books are there in a diet? And in the bookstore? It's like thousands of books on how to lose weight. You know how you lose weight? Stop eating. You're going to lose weight. You want to build business practice. Be really nice to your patients and have good clinical skills.
And study hard. But nobody wants to do that because it's boring. There's really no I don't know anybody that became successful overnight. It's really, really hard, you know? And the ones that did like Britney Spears and Michael Jackson, they had hard lives, you know?
Right. Absolutely.
But it's… I don't see too many dentists becoming great. I mean, only on Instagram, not in real life.
So now I'm ranting.
That's right. So absolutely appreciate that answer, Dr. Sonic, where you showed, you know, if you're having a culture problem, that's really a hiring problem, and to answer, uh, you know, if patients are actually going to start saying yes more.
Well, you'll have to start at that process and be as adamant as Dr. Sonic is with hiring people slow.
Uh, now let's move on to some of our registrants' questions, uh, here. Right.
So our 1st question is for, um… Oh, okay, it's a fellow specialist in the room, uh, Dr. John Parnoff, uh, an owner and periodontist, is looking for the playbook. So, Dr. Parnoff asks, does the anti-PPO transition look different for specialty practice versus a general practice, and what is the first step.
A special list should take to protect their referral base while dropping plans. Dr. Sonic, would you like to take a gander at this?
Yeah. I know John, his good friend. He's a fellow periodontist at Connecticut. I've known him for 40, 35, 40 years.
Oh, okay.
So I never worry about competition from the specialists of protecting, you know, or protecting my referral base. I figure, you know, because a lot of my patients come from patients. I think if you provide a certain quality of service and you're there.
Um, you don't really have to worry about that. So I don't practice defensively. Fax is very proactively. And, um, you know, I just try to provide not the best only quality service, but the best experience for the patient, because patients don't know the difference between my implant and Parnoff's implant.
you know, they have no idea if one's better than the other, you know, and there may be a difference, there may not be.
And it's really they're going to know the difference between how they're treated, you know, really not by me or Parnoff, but by me and my team or their team. Most people leave the dental practice because of the team, not because of the doctor, you know, because it's usually the team that they're responding with.
So I have never taken insurance. So I started in 1985, and I was the sixth periodontist in the town of 65,000 people. So I opened up my hometown, which was saturated, and I decided I was going to develop a.
fee-for-service practice. It took me 3 years to become profitable. So it wasn't really a great financial move early on.
But it has become one. And when my partner joined me 12 years ago, you know, I had a practice that was pretty busy, but it wasn't full-time for two people. He goes, well, maybe I should take insurance. I said, no, don't. He really wanted to. We wouldn't let him.
And now he's booked two and a half months in advance. And now my third partner, you know, she didn't even ask. We told her she's not going to, and now she's getting busy, you know, but we already have the tracks laid, you know, for them.
So I think I don't think there are a lot of people out there providing really great care, not in terms of the quality of care. I'm talking about really good care and like taking care of people. You think about this, Don. Anybody here, how many restaurants do you go to over and over again because you just love it. It's a great experience.
You know, there aren't that many. Now I'm in New York City. There's 8,600 restaurants here. You know, I go to the same four or five.
All the time, you know? Actually, my book is patterned after Danny Meyer, who's a restaurateur, you know, the Gramercy Tavern, which is one of the best restaurants in New York City.
And you know how many, you know what I'm going to in a few weeks? I'm going to a hospitality convention, not a dental convention, but Will Gederia, and it's sold out, and I'll probably be the only dentist there. It should be filled with dentists learning how to give great hospitality.
Yeah.
Okay, so perhaps is that your 1st step? Going to a hospitality convention.
Yeah, you gotta look at yourself as a hospitality, and who happens to be Duke. You go to a great restaurant, you don't want good hospitality, you want great food, and you want people to treat you really well, and you want to be nicely lit, and the music should be good, and it shouldn't smell when you go into the bathroom, it's neat and clean, you know. I've walked out of restaurants because of the because of.
Okay.
One of those things. One of my senses being alienated? And the same… I mean, I… I'm like… I become such a critic, I can't go anywhere with, like, seeing everything that's wrong.
Right.
And patients are the same way too. They may not see it, but they're going to feel it. They're going to feel the smell, they're going to feel the fact that you have old magazines, they're going to see you snap at your staff, they're going to see the fact that they're on the phone and the glass door is in front. There's so many things that people do wrong.
Because… They're not paying attention. They don't realize how important it is. Nobody thinks about this, you know. We were talking about, what did they teach us in business and business in dental school? Right now, I don't know if you've all seen it. There's an article written. Actually, my friend, this was written about in in the Wall Street Journal about the millionaire next door, the dentists.
But it really it made the dentist seem like they're very wealthy, but the dentists aren't… dentists all struggle. Most dentists aren't wealthy. They start… they come out with $600,000 in debt and got to work their butt off, you know, to get out of there. And that's a problem. I mean, I have… I was the same way. I had that kind of debt, and have 600, 400.
But it was a lot. And then to build the practice, which may cost you a million or 2 million to build, and then you're you're making all this money, but it's going to pay overhead.
You think, well, I'm going to cut corners. I'm going to take insurance. I want the chair fold.
and the chair's full, and you're making less money because it's, you know, you reduce… you reduced your profit margin by 50% because you're taking insurance.
So yeah.
Right. Dr. Sonic, we are going to move into the next question, which might have another answer on top of this to Dr. Parnoff. Daniel, next we have a question about the announcement phase. So, uh, Dr. Latanya, Kelly, and, uh.
Dr. Michael Tooman. Oh, are asking about the how. So Danielle, when a practice decides to go out of network, what is the best way to notify the patients? Is it a mass email before the next recall, or is it better to have that conversation face to face?
Yeah, I'm a firm believer that this conversation is at the appointment, knee to knee with your patients and really sort of talking them through this process. I have gone out of network with that big bad Delta a few times, and.
It's been in every area, so I've really found that the patients respond well when we're, again, transparent. You've built trust, they understand why they're staying with your practice.
we didn't see this huge 30% drop in patient base. What we did see was that maybe they trickled away for a little bit of time, and they came right back because they loved the team. They loved the doctor, they loved the way that they were treated.
But certainly, I don't think if we would have sent out a mass text or an email or, you know, anything like that, a letter that they would have felt the same way. I think they would have felt a little blindsided if we didn't have that conversation with them, their favorite hygienist, their assistants, the doctor.
really talking them through with this process was going to look like. And in most cases, I started this process a year in advance.
Check. Now, before we move on to the next registering question, I do want to remind our attendees, please do ask your questions right now. Drop them in the Q&A section, or else even in the chat, the chat is a little bit busy, but the Q&A section is great so that I can pick them up in a few minutes and ask all the panelists their thoughts on.
Your burning questions. So do make the best use of your time that you have invested thus far. And now, uh… Dr. Sonic, do you actually have something to say about this? I'm curious, when we're dropping out of PPOs, how are you deciding to really notify your patients?
If I was going to, well, I've never dropped out, but I would always tell them, you know, some patients do need. I think it's important to tell the patients and to be open.
Right.
Um, and you can tell them personally if you're going to be dropping out and you can say, hey, listen, after all these years together, you know, we really appreciate the relationship, but we've made a decision. You don't have to tell them why you've made the decision.
That's right.
So we've made a decision, and I use things that are very non-computational. We've made a decision to move in a different direction, because we're going to feel it will benefit our patients. They don't know what that means, okay? But it will benefit them, because you won't be stressed, and you'll be able to provide better quality care, because you'll be able to afford a new handpiece, you know, it doesn't break every other day.
Yes.
And you'll be able to improve the quality of the lives of the people that work for you. You know, you won't be as stressed. I'll tell you this, there's nothing like making money to decrease stress, you know? It does ease things. When you're struggling to do payroll.
And you can't, you know, you can't get new drapes, you can't paint the office, and you can't afford to have it cleaned.
You know, and the carpet's ragged. I mean, it makes a difference.
Right.
Um, so… I think we're in a phenomenal profession. We can do so many things, and we get the help. We get to help people and be compensated for it.
you know, build a team. But it's difficult.
Absolutely. Now it is difficult.
Yeah. But it's fun. For some people. Some people hate it. Now, half of all physicians would not go back to medical school because they're burnt out.
You know, a lot of people do burnout. I was just with my mentor yesterday. He is actually dying of ALS and he's 80 now. And I visited him about every three months in Atlanta, and all my professors were there. These guys are in their 80s now, and they were all we're sitting around talking these, you know, in their 70s, 80s, 60s.
All my friends in Atlanta that went to Emory with, and we were like talking passionately about dentistry, just the clinical part. My wife's looking at us like, you guys are such nerds, you know? My mentors are like 80, and we're still talking like that. We're and I feel like we're lucky that we, like, like this. So.
But I think we liked it because we all work real hard to get good at it and serve our patients. You know, if I just did it to make a living, no, no. And I made a good living with it, but that's not why I went to school.
You know, it took me a while to get to the point where I made a good living.
Right.
So, but they can't fire you. You know, I'm at work… I'm not working on Wall Street, not working for the local corporation.
There we go. Now, I got another question to Danielle. The next one is a bit of a tactical question from Dr. Andrew Olson. Dr. Olson is asking about the transition discount. Is it a good business policy to offer temporary discounts to out-of-network patients, perhaps.
On their hygiene visit to keep them from leaving while they adjust to the new free structure.
Okay.
Um, I don't know that I would call that a discount. I think that there's ways to phrase that when and I look at this like when a new practice owner is transitioning into ownership, and they're buying a practice, and you're working through.
credentialing things and trying to stay in the same networks that your cell or doctor was in.
So we're kind of looking at the same thing. And I think that the appropriate way is to, again, be very transparent with your patients. You want to tell them exactly what they're going to see. You may see some things come back on your explanation of benefits. It's going to look a little bit different than it has in the past. Please understand that we're working through this process.
And you know, it's going to take X amount of time to work through this.
They're always welcome to ask questions. But my big go-to with an office is always this. And I said it earlier, somehow in dentistry, we went down this huge rabbit hole of having to explain everything in insurance to our patients versus.
really just creating value in what it is that we do. And I think if we can get back there, I am so hopeful that we're gonna get back there one day, that we do not have to have these insurance conversations, whether it's transitional, going in and out of network.
Whatever that looks like, but I think honesty with patients on where it is that you sit.
Um, I'm always cautionary with discounts when we're talking about insurance, because there are things we can do, and there are things we cannot do. So I, you know, it's always… We have to be very clear on when we use the word discount and we're talking about insurance plans. So, you know, I'm just going to kind of leave that there.
Right.
We are going out of insurance. So the question was, when we are going out of network for our membership plan just to offer them a little bit more incentive to stay on a fee for service.
Well, okay, so what I do see a lot of these offices doing is we're talking about going out of network.
But they're not really going out of network. They're not becoming a full fee-for-service office. What they're doing is they're still tied to insurance because they're still billing insurance, they're still doing insurance verifications. Now they're just doing it as an out-of-network provider, a non-par provider.
So they've still kind of put themselves into this category of an insurance provider just as a non-PAR provider. So I think that there'd have to be a real clear line for that office that's wanting to do this. Are you wanting to be full fee for service?
Or are you still going to function as an insurance provider with this plan just out of network? And how do we want to?
offer that to the patients. If it's doing a discount during that process, sure.
Check. Now, Dr. Sonic, when you're building towards bigger, more complex cases, how do you make sure the everyday restorative work is still carrying the practice when those larger cases aren't coming inconsistently?
Yeah, you gotta take care of it. It's a good question. You gotta take care of the basics. I talk about this a lot. We we have.
We have… when a patient comes into our practice.
I make them commit to getting their teeth clean every what I think it is 3 to 4 or 5 months before I treat them. So if you're a new patient in my office, Don, at the first visit and you need a lot of work, I say, you know, I'll treat you, but you got to commit to maintaining your health.
Because of my treatment, you know, is successful. You don't maintain it, you know, it's like, you know, driving an expensive car and not changing the oil.
filling the gas during the maintenance will break down. So we have a very strong maintenance practice and we have um we have two or three hygienists every day in our practice. And I don't look at the hygiene practice to do the little things or do anything. I want them to be maintained there.
So even though I do a lot of full mouth rehabilitation and a lot of anterior aesthetic implants, and.
you know, I guess people like to do the big stuff, they think that's a lot of fun, but unless you do the little things and you take care of the basics, you won't do the big stuff, and you really turn your back on your patients. And I know a lot of people… there's some doctors in town, if I refer them over to, like, other specialists that are very firm, something that's not, like, a big thing.
No, we don't do that anymore. And I always think you need to take care of the people. And that's sort of why we became doctors, and we took a Hippocratic oath to really to give the best care. So when you do that.
You're always busy. You know, but during a recession, when things are really bad, we've always been busy. And not all contractors are busy. You know, the roofers and the guys that do the side and the painting, the electricians, you know, you can't get an electrician when the economy is good. You just can't forget getting a plumber.
You can't get them because they're too busy for you, except the really good ones, the ones that are really busy will still come out and will still answer your phone calls. And during the recession, those are the ones that stay busy and everybody else goes, well, I'm not doing so well the recession, the recession. I've never felt the recession in our practice.
Because we've always given really, really good care to people that are there, and people would want to come in for that, because the value is there. So I don't think you can neglect doing that. Oh, I'm just… I just want to do implants, you know, forget it. I just I don't want to do a little abscess on a 4-year-old or a kid. We're just going to take me 1 hour, but I have to give them my time. That's still very important.
And that's really how you build your practice by doing the little things. You know, that's really, really important. That's a great question. It's something I'm talking about a lot. I put out a YouTube two or three YouTube videos actually every week, and I've really been talking about the importance of hygiene and talking to basics. I'm writing an article. I just gave the closing lecture at the Academy of Oscene Integration, which is a.
pretty well regarded implant organization, and my… my… I gave the closing lecture, and it was all about the future of our patients that we treat. It's really taking good care of them, and so the Dean of Stony Brook asked me to write an article on commitment.
Because no one ever talks about that. No one really ever talks about, yeah, I'm going to do a full mouth implant rehabilitation, but you gotta get your teeth cleaned every three months, because why'd you lose your teeth to begin with? Because of hygiene. So that's a really important question, and I think it's incumbent upon us as a profession to take care of the people that we are privileged to serve.
You're welcome.
Check. Thank you very much, Dr. Sonic, for that very comprehensive answer. Commitment. I don't think it gets spoken.
enough about in our conversations. Right, Danielle, we must move on. So when a practice tries to win back lapse patients using only automated messages and no one on the team ever personally reaches out.
What tends to break down in actually getting those patients back?
Yeah. This is a huge one for me. One of one of the things that I do is actually reactivate patients. And.
I love AI. Everyone hear me say that. I love it. But I don't love it for this. I think that I think that when our dental offices feel like they are too busy to pick up the phone and call the patients that they have let walk out the door.
we are… we've lost an opportunity. And the way I always explain this to teams is that, and to doctors, I look at the value that they spend, I look at all the money they're spending on marketing.
And then I show them the number of patients that are walking out every single day, every week, every month.
And what it takes a person to just sit at the desk for an hour, two hours, to make a few phone calls versus an automated system. The automated systems right now have about 4% return where a human still has anywhere from 17 to 27%. And I know that because I have a team that does it.
And I know those statistics, like, the back of my hand. And it's so important to still have that connection, to be able to hear your team smiling from behind the phone. Without that, your patient retention is just not going… you're wasting money marketing. So we could talk marketing all day long, but if you're not going to retain your patients and get on the phone.
When you realize that there's a leak. The text message blast and all of those really cool tools that we have, they're not necessarily going to pick up the Slack for us.
Check. Alrighty.
Well, can I ask you a question? What was that number again? Ai gets what kind of return and a human gets what kind?
They're about 4 to 7% AI and humans can get up to 20 in the high mid to high 20s.
Yeah.
There we go. That personal touch cannot be overstated. Absolutely. The critical last piece of the puzzle, and the one, perhaps, that, you know, will allow us to thrive in the future, the human touch.
Uh, now, Dr. Sonic, Danielle, thank you so much for, uh, you know, the, uh, anti-PPO system.
With regards to the clinical and business asset, the human connection we build remains steadily the greatest asset that we have. Now it's time for a bit of an audience Q&A session here. So let me see. I know we had one question over here.
Oh, that got answered right. Paulina. Okay.
So, all right, let me share the screen real quickly then.
Nice.
To our audience members, if you have any burning questions right now, feel free to raise your hand. Well, raise your hand as in, uh, drop it here on Zoom. I will enable you to speak out your question. That way it's much more easier than typing it out, if that.
is something that you would like to get answered.
So please feel free to do that. I have one last question here. Perhaps.
Okay.
This is open to the whole panel. But final question from Dr. Mike Castillo, a dentist, is asking about scaling without burnout. And Dr. Juan Lee tuning in from Canada is curious about the role of AI. So.
Perhaps Dr. Sonic can start us off over here. How do you see technology and AI helping a PPO-independent office maintain that high human touch while keeping the team efficient and scalable?
What's the scaling? It was scalable. Yeah, well, we we we don't use a tremendous amount of AI in our practice. I use a lot. I just came back from a convention. So I use it in all my education and writing and presentations, and I'm constantly putting everything through it.
Um, I think it's good for, you know, x-rays, you know, to look at it. I don't know if it's necessary, but it certainly helps educate the patients. It's a better way to do it. There's a lot of ways you can do it the front desk to look at the data. We have a way that we look at our case acceptance rate through AI. We put that through a program. We have various things.
So, I don't know if you need AI to initially scale, but if you get extremely busy, you have a lot of data, and you have a lot of people working for you, you want to look at… you want to be able to keep track of all that data, production per hour, case acceptance rate, where your patients are coming from. You can learn it from marketing.
It's just control. It's just it's phenomenal for keeping control of a large reams of data. Depends on the size of your practice. But unless you're doing the little things, then you're going to just have a large practice that makes you feel very impersonal, you know, with the AI. I mean, I've… I mean, try… I checked, you know, I tried to make reservations on phone today, and it was, like, 40 minutes, and I didn't get anybody. It was very frustrating.
Yeah.
You know, it's it's like what Danielle said, you know, the human touch is really important. So I think, you know, someone who is very much, you know, customer centric and very much hospitality oriented, I think there's going to be… You can have AI, which is going to be organizing data, and it's going to be making people very, very impersonal. Now, I'm in New York City and I'm in a gym in New York. Nobody's talking to each other. I watch the craziest thing today. I watched the trainer, and…
The client, okay, they were training, they're both on their cell phone texting as they were lifting weights, okay? And they weren't even talking to each other. They weren't even texting about weights. So they're like, that's the future. So if you can be personal in this AI world, that's the win. Control the data.
And then you still need some humans in there. Because I think if you listen to Tony Robbins, one of the things that we all need is love and connection. And everybody wants to be loved and feel connected to. I'm not really feeling the love from an AI bot. It's going to be a little bit different.
Hmm. Okay.
Yeah, anyway, you know, although a lot of people do, you know. It's sad.
Oh, yeah. Oh yeah, that's a very interesting tangent right there. Ai and love. But right, we have arrived at the end of the event.
Here, I do want to get one last, uh… take away from our panelists, what is the first thing, uh, that our audience members can do when they show up at their practice tomorrow that can help them go towards a more high-value.
patient-centric practice and stop being a PPO-only practice. Let's start with you, Danielle.
Oh, how did I know you were going to call on me first? I'm gonna say that if you're not currently talking about this consistently, whether it's in your morning huddle or monthly meetings. Make a conversation consistent about.
how you're connecting and what you're doing differently with your patients, whether it's through phone calls or handoffs. And even what that looks like between you and your teammates.
its consistency is key with this, and learning communication skills is huge. And so if it's not consistent, it's not going to happen. And so I would say, walk back into your practice and learn how you're going to communicate. Talk about how you're going to communicate different.
Consistency is the key, and consistency in communication makes a huge difference. Dominica.
Yeah.
I would say, and just to piggyback on what Danielle alluded, you want to make sure that we stop apologizing for cost and we start communicating the value of the work that we provide as healthcare providers.
We get to take care of patients, we get to care about their health, we get to improve their quality of lives. I know that sometimes, you know, we get stuck in the, oh, it's so hard, it's an uphill battle on fighting the insurance, but.
At the end of the day, we get to do those things. And it's all about perspective.
perspective. That's very interesting. Absolutely. Keeping a very grateful perspective as to what an amazing profession we are able to contribute to and help change people's life.
It's so important. Dr. Sonic, the last one is for you, sir.
What's the key takeaway here?
All right. Either tomorrow or sometime this week, maybe when you're not working.
Walk into your office. I may believe you're a patient. Just sit in your reception area and look around.
And see what you see, the good, the bad. Look at the paint, smell it, does it smell good? Look at the magazines. Do you have fresh fruit? Listen to the way your team is answering the phone, how they're greeting people. Look around your property. Just do a… A visual, you know, and listen and smell, and see everything, and go, what can be made better? And take some notes. I will I on my website, michelsonic.com, I have a document called the little things. It's 8 pages of things that we do in our practice that make us unique.
You know, download the document and make your own, and actually have your team write down at the morning huddle, say, you know, by 4 o'clock today, I want you to each write down 10 things we do that make our office special.
And that's how we created ours. And you start to develop that culture within your office of, like, we're special, we're good. And then shine a light on it every day. Say, hey, what have you done today? It's special? So we shine a light on everybody every day, saying, hey, look what Taylor did, look what so-and-so did.
We actually have. Oh, here's one more idea, too. Create a chief of hospitality in your office. We have one person in our office. Their main job is to be chief of hospitality. And what she does is she brings great experiences to everybody, patients, team members, vendors, anybody in.
the life of our practice.
Wonderful. Thank you very much, Dr. Sonit, for that great reminder and a very innovative look.
at what it really means. to elevate the patient experience and what it'll take right then, a couple of reminders before the closing eco marketing complementary marketing strategy meeting is available for you to make use of. So for our attendees, when a patient's in your city search for perhaps implant dentist near me, Invisalign cost or veneers before and after on their Google. Well, now Gemini.
or else ChatGPT, does your practice show up as the trusted choice? So make sure it is the one that gets found and chosen. Links in the chat, book your session before it fills up. And then, of course.
We got to remind about the CE credits. Make sure you fill up the form that is being dropped in the chat right now to get your two CE credits. Do not worry if you missed that link, we'll send it to you via email, and if you can fill it out within one week, we can get it processed to you within 2 to 3 weeks.
Due to the nature of the heavy event flow we got going on.
Please do give us that grace. Then… Right.
Amazing.
So, dear panelists, thank you so much for sharing your wonderful insight and experience here with us tonight. For our attendees, thank you so much for investing the time into your practice, into your patient journey, and really committing to.
The art and the profession of dentistry. Uh, with that being said, it has been my honor and privilege to host this session for y'all, and until the next Reducing Insurance Dependence.
Academy's event. Take care, everyone. Good night. All the best.
Thank you, Don.
Thank you.
And someone asked, how do we access the recording? It'll be in your email. Do not worry about that. One last quick reminder.